<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A clear voice of truth sounded forth, and as an ensign lifted up and displayed in answer to the proceedings of the Christians by name in Asia, by way of controversie and expostulation : together with savoury and wholesome admonishments, which may become of good use and profitable to all that read with a single eye, and understand with an upright heart : also the same somewhat tends by way of gentle reproof to their hasty and inequitable proceedings against the innocent servants, messengers and living witnesses of the living and true God : yet with tendernesse of an upright heart and spirit (not onely of a free born English-man, but also of a true Christian) from the same hand its principally directed to the Lord Embassasdor (so called) in Constantinople, and to the English Company of Merchants and Factors in Smyrna, with somewhat to the merchants in Genoa, tendred again by way of visitation, and that from God, for them and others in Italy to consider and not reject to their own hurt.</title>
            <author>D. B. (Daniel Baker), fl. 1650-1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 81 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29602</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B482</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22863</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12125437</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12125437</idno>
            <idno type="VID">54583</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29602)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54583)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 756:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A clear voice of truth sounded forth, and as an ensign lifted up and displayed in answer to the proceedings of the Christians by name in Asia, by way of controversie and expostulation : together with savoury and wholesome admonishments, which may become of good use and profitable to all that read with a single eye, and understand with an upright heart : also the same somewhat tends by way of gentle reproof to their hasty and inequitable proceedings against the innocent servants, messengers and living witnesses of the living and true God : yet with tendernesse of an upright heart and spirit (not onely of a free born English-man, but also of a true Christian) from the same hand its principally directed to the Lord Embassasdor (so called) in Constantinople, and to the English Company of Merchants and Factors in Smyrna, with somewhat to the merchants in Genoa, tendred again by way of visitation, and that from God, for them and others in Italy to consider and not reject to their own hurt.</title>
                  <author>D. B. (Daniel Baker), fl. 1650-1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: Daniel Baker.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:54583:1"/>
            <p>A CLEAR VOICE OF TRUTH Sounded forth, And as an Enſign lifted up and diſplayed, in anſwer to the proceedings of the Chriſtians by name in <hi>Aſia,</hi> by way of Controverſie and Expoſtulation; to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with Savoury and Wholeſome Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, which may become of good uſe and profitable to all that read with a ſingle eye, and underſtand with an upright heart.</p>
            <p>Alſo the ſame ſomewhat tends by way of gentle reproof to their haſty and unequitable proceedings againſt the Innocent Servants, Meſſengers and living Witneſſes of the Living and True God.</p>
            <p>Yet with the tenderneſſe of an upright Heart and Spirit (not onely of a free born <hi>Engliſh</hi>-man, but alſo of a True Chriſtian) from the ſame hand its principally directed to the Lord Embaſſador (ſo called) in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Company of Merchants and Factors in <hi>Smyrna,</hi> with ſomewhat to the Merchants in <hi>Genoa,</hi> tendred again by way of Viſitation, and that from God, for them and others in <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> to conſider and not reject to their own hurt.</p>
            <q>Bleſſed are they which are perſecuted for Righteouſneſſe ſake, for theirs is the Kingd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m of Heaven, <bibl>
                  <hi>Mat. 5.10.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the year, 1662.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:54583:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54583:2"/>
            <head>AN EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THere is certainly a very Pretious, Noble, Royal, Long-Suffering Seed of the Eternal God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth, the which in theſe latter dayes of our age ſince the long night of Apostacy [from Chriſt and his Holy Apoſtles and Saints life] to which the Eternal Arm of the Lord God is manifeſtly revealed unto eternal Salvation and perfect Redemption, in and by the <hi>Light</hi> of the Lord Jeſus (the Immanuel) who as truly <hi>light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth every man,</hi> as he taſted <hi>Death</hi> for every man that cometh into the World, and this pretious Seed which is the <hi>Light</hi> that is ſown for the Righteous,<note n="*" place="margin">And the People become perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Righteous that believe in and obey the ſame light of Jeſus, and are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by made partakers of the Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and ſo of the ſame nature of God, which comes to be revealed from faith to ſaith in Male and Female, for which end the light which is the Seed is ſown in the heart, is the Light ſhines in darkneſs which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends not that which is the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in the earthen Veſſel as a pearl hid in a field, and is the good thing which can give the knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Jeſus Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.19. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.19. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</note> the ſame hath been viſited from on high as a thing hid in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity in many, under the Region and Shaddow of Death and Deſtruction, ſo that it hath been quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and revived mightily to the amazement and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhment of Kindreds, Nations, Tongues and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples becauſe of the arm of the Lords Salvation, with which he hath ariſen in his Majeſty and ſhaken terribly
<pb facs="tcp:54583:3"/> the Earth and Heavens alſo, and made the Keepers of the ſtrong Mans Houſe to tremble, and by his power of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs to bind him and ſpoile his goods; So that the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting <hi>Light</hi> hath ſent his Word (of Power) into <hi>Jacob,</hi> and it hath lighted upon Poor diſtreſſed <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in whoſe houſe he, the Lord God (that Spirit) hath promiſed to dwell in the midst for ever, as in the <hi>Antient dayes,</hi> and many of the Eternal Off-ſpring of Life which is the <hi>Light of men,</hi> having gladly received the Word of Life, not from man nor by man that ſhall dye, but from his mouth, <hi>that was dead and is alive, and behold he liveth for evermore,</hi> that leads his Flock like a good Shepherd to Living Springs and Fountains, which are as wells <hi>ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up into everlaſting Life,</hi> in them that believe, as the Scripture hath ſaid, <hi>John 4. John. 7.38.30.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And theſe as Lambs among Wolves, having the bleſsed Life and Salvation to Proclaim in Faithfulneſs, travelling in their innocent integrity on this wiſe, as our Brethren the Prophets and Fathers of old did from one Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to another People; Now why are the Nations angry? and why do the Mighty and Potentates of the Earth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine and take Counſel together againſt the Lord and his <hi>Anointed?</hi> Is it not becauſe the Eternal God is provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them to jealouſie and to anger with a fooliſh Nation, with them which are deemed not a People, who are Poor, Afflicted, Deſpiſed, Deſtreſſed on every hand, yet not forſaken of the Lord their Rock, their Strength, <hi>Deut. 32.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now it came to paſs that after the Lord God <hi>[who formeth the Mountains and Createth the Wind which obeyeth him,] Amos. 4. laſt.</hi> had given three more of my Brethren together with me a good paſſage from the Land of our Nativity to <hi>Italy,</hi> namely, to <hi>Legorne,</hi> where two of us, (to wit) <hi>John Stubs</hi> and <hi>Henry Fell,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:54583:3"/> was ordered of the Lord to paſſe from thence towards <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria</hi> and they became obedient; and it came to paſs alſo by the permiſſion of God who ſuffered the men of our own Nation to Baniſh and expel them away from that Region and Coaſt, where they gave a ſound of the <hi>Mighty Day of Gods viſitation,</hi> and ſaith Chriſt, <hi>as they have done unto me, ſo will they do unto you, &amp;c.</hi> The <hi>Gada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renes</hi> loved their Swine and beſought Chriſt to depart out of their Coaſt, and them that Rebel against the <hi>Light,</hi> ſaith, <hi>depart from us</hi> (even to the moſt High) <hi>for we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire not the knowledge of thy wayes,</hi> Job. <hi>21.</hi> Job. <hi>24. 13, 14.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And furthermore my Dear Brother <hi>Richard Scoſtrope</hi> my Companion in Tribulation and in the Power of God, by which we were alſo ordered (having no impoſition from any mortal man on our Conſciences God is witneſs) was ordained of God to paſs Eastward, towards <hi>Aſia,</hi> namely, to <hi>Smyrna,</hi> intending alſo to travel further (if the Lord ſuffered not Sathan to hinder;) and behold when we came there, having enjoyed the benefit of a good paſſage, that the Merchants and Great men and others of our own Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion did not a little perplex and burthen themſelves not only at our bodily preſence, but alſo with our faithful and true innocent and harmleſs meſſage of life, and glad ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of Salvation to the Nations, and verily they cannot deny but that our behaviour and deportment (if they ſpeak truth) was ſuch as we profeſſed in Words and Doctrine in all good Converſation whileſt we abode among them, as examples in the manifold Diſpenſations of the grace of God Almighty, to whom be the Glory over all, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We being at our firſt coming ſent for before the Conſul of the Nation, gave him a good and ſober information of the intent of our hearts as God had ordered and determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:54583:4"/> in ſome meaſure (to try them) and he ſaid that he muſt give account to the Lord Ambaſſadour and ſend ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings to <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> to him, and he could not ſuffer us to paſs further till he had received information in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now we ſaw not of our departure from <hi>Smyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> imediately, and ſeeing that they did intend to write, many of them being evil affected with prejudice and ſuch like ſurmiſings againſt us that loved them, and travelled in the love and Spirit of Gods Truth for their eternal good freely, albeit they hated us without cauſe as it befell our Lord and Maſter; I alſo was moved in the fear of the Lord to write and give the Ambaſſadour an honeſt and true information of the intent of our hearts, to the end he might be honeſtly warned of receiving any evil and falſe intelligence that he may not conſent with the ſame, nor with the ground of it to joyn or ſtretch forth his hand therewith againſt the Lord, his Truth and innocent Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:54583:4"/>
            <p>THE Copy of the Letter is ſeen meet to be inſerted here following, ſeeing the ſame was made leight of, and rejected as a thing of nought, as many have done to their own hurt and condemnation, namely, <hi>O. C.</hi> and the many Parliaments in their dayes paſt, in which the Eternal God tryed them (what if I ſay to the uttermoſt) before he ſmote, and broke and ſhattered them to pieces as Potters Veſſells, and wherled them up and down as Clouds of Tempeſts and Darkneſs, as it were from one end of the Land to the other in his ſore diſpleaſure (in the ſight of the Nations, to the final deſtruction of many of them that tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the back; Albeit they ſeemed to have their face towards the good Day of their Viſitation from on High, which they wofully ſinned away, and the juſt recompence of reward as a fruit of their own doings, even in the ſight of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, fell upon them as a weight too heavy for them to bear, and as great judgements from the ſame Hand of God is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in ſtore, and is ready to be revealed and executed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Heads of them that walk in the ſame wayes and paths of unrighteouſneſſe, which provokes the Lord to his Face, I ſpeak not on this wiſe to (upbraid without the Fear of the Lord) the generation thats paſſed away, and ſeems to be laid in the duſt of the Earth, but rather that the preſent ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of men, of what Name or Denomination they were, are or may be under, that have but ſomewhat of the Fear and Zeal of the God of Truth in their Hearts, thereby to be warned in their day, and not to make the evil example of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to be ſo to them, as evil to follow it, nay but contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, which is ſo far acceptable to God, for <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah</hi> and the old World, were and are evident examples of the ſore diſpleaſure of the Eternal God of vengeance, to whom it peculiarly and properly belongeth, and he will certainly repay <hi>Fury to his Adverſaries, and Recompence to his Enemies,</hi> when he awakes and ſtirs up his ſtrength as <hi>a MIGHTY ONE (the KING, the Lord of Hoſts is his Name)</hi> to bend his Bow, and whet his glittering Sword, he will caſt up, cut down
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:54583:5"/> and overturn, and not ſpare to ſpend his Arrows of famine and deſtruction, and let them fly with his outſtretched Arm of ſtrength, to ſmite and ſtrike into the Hearts of the double-minded, ſo that his anger ſhall ſmoak in the fiery Zeal of his Eternal Majeſty againſt ſuch a one, that being often repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, goeth on ſtill in his iniquities, he ſhall ſuddenly be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, and that without remedy, as ſaith one in a certain place, <hi>Prov.</hi> 29. yet the Nations of men may certainly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that the moſt High holds forth his Eternal Name, as he is the Lord God, long ſuffering and of great goodneſs, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther delighteth he in the deſtruction of any, but rather in their return unto the Wiſdom of the Juſt, unto Eternal Life in it to live for ever, and not to die in their ſins, for as he is the <hi>Light</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and his <hi>Holy One</hi> for a <hi>flame,</hi> and a conſuming fire to burn up Bryars and Thorns againſt the workers of Iniquity, ſo is he a God of Judgement, <hi>and bleſſed are all they that wait for his Salvation,</hi> and put their truſt in him, he will ſhew them his Covenant, and eſtabliſh them in the ſame, in which they ſhall not be confounded, neither be aſhamed, nor yet ſhall any make them afraid, but quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and aſſurance for ever ſhall be their reward in Eternal Peace and Bleſſedneſs, together with him and the Spirits of Juſt men made perfect, on this wiſe my Soul in life breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and travels for the Reſtauration of all things, into the Glorious Liberty and Freedom of the harmleſs Sons of God.</p>
            <p>Verily, the Eternal love of my God thats ſhed abroad within my heart, its much enlarged to ſtream forth Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally, even to the whole Creation that travels in pain under the Bondage of Corruption, over which mine eyes have poured forth many tears, and in the brokenneſſe of my very heart have I dolefully Lamented and Mourned for the ſame, but at preſent, I am neceſſitated to proceed on to what is before mine eye, as I have began concerning this little Treatiſe.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:54583:5"/>
                  <head>The Copy of the Letter.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>FRIEND,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THy Everlaſting Honour and Wel-being with the Lord and with the Spirits of juſt men our ſoul wiſheth right well, ſo peace be unto thee.</p>
                  <p>This is that thou may [according to the Juſt, Noble Principle of God in thee] have a right underſtanding of ſomewhat of the Truth, Innocency and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>prightneſs of our hearts, who are the Servants of the One True and Living God and Father of all Truth, and called by his grace of life, which in our hearts we have received gladly, to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare to the Nations, even the ſame grace that hath brought Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to us, the ſame alſo that appeareth unto all men without reſpect of perſons that they may be ſaved from the wrath to come, by which grace of life (I ſay) we are called to peace and good will to all men (as our Fathers were) in the ſame to forſake the Pollutions of the World and our Native Country, Kindred and Fathers Houſe to do and ſuffer the will of God, and keep his Commandments which are not grievous to us in the life of our Obedience to his Bleſsed Will, who called and ſent us into theſe parts whether the Sons of men believe us or not, or hear or forbear; And ſeeing the God of our Life hath bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and proſpered us hitherto in our journey, we have the Living Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of the Spirit of Life witneſſing to the ſame in our Conſciences, and to the Truth of what is here written unto thee.</p>
                  <p>And foraſmuch as we understand from the Conſul here that we ſhall not by him be admitted to paſs further without thy advice or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, therefore have we freedom, and in the fear of the Lord ſeen meet to let thee know ſomewhat from our hands, as to the preſent ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of our God, whoſe Power, Favour and life in his Covenant of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Light and Peace we poſseſſe <hi>Glory to his Name,</hi> for which our lives are not dear unto us, which are (alſo) in our hands to ſerve the Lord his Truth and People, and to the end thou may not, in any wiſe be as an Inſtrument to ſtop or let the work of God from going on, by the hand of his Meſſengers and Ambaſsadours of peace, Wherefore in the fear and tender love of the God of Heaven is this to be laid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee (to warn thee) as thou art in thy place of Authority (which
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:54583:6"/> we own, eſteem and honour in the Lord, one of us (being two) ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a meſſage from the Lord of Heaven to the Prince (or Emperour) of the <hi>Turks,</hi> and well will it be with the men of our own Nation if they be not found ſetting themſelves againſt the ſervice of God, his Truth and People whom he alone will make a bleſſing to Nations, that ſhall ſurely proſper <hi>without Bow, or Sword, or viſible Weapons of war,</hi> the Lord hath ſpoken it, and the Propheſie ſhall as ſurely be fulfilled in its time or ſeaſon.</p>
                  <p>So the Lord give thee wiſdome and a Noble underſtanding ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his determinate Counſel therewith to honour him in thy place of Judicature; and ſo my Spirit ſaith, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Smyrna,</hi> 
                        <date>the ſixth month of the Year, <hi>1661.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>I am thy Friend, and ſo to the whole Creation of God,</hi> Daniel Baker. Richard Scoſtrope.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>NOw it was ſo that after this was ſent, we notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſought daily for paſſage convenient to <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople,</hi> and at laſt it preſented by way of a <hi>Dutch</hi> Ship, and we ſpake to the Commander for the ſame end on board the ſaid Veſſel, but before She ſailed away, a Warrant was forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with given out and ſent from the Kings Embaſſadour to <hi>Smyrna,</hi> which men of high degree gladly received and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted the ſame againſt us, to expell us from their Coaſts, and ſeparate us from their company, all be it we were not in any wiſe chargable unto them, neither did eat any mans bread for nought.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="warrant">
               <body>
                  <head>A Coppy of the Warrant which came from the hand of the Kings Ambaſſadour, and proſecuted by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in <hi>Smyrna</hi> in <hi>Aſia</hi> againſt two ſervants and witneſſes for God and his Truth and People called <hi>Quakers.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>WHereas we are informed that there is lately arrived with the Zant Frigot, one <hi>Daniel Baker</hi> with his companion, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called by the name of Quakers, with intention to come up to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:54583:6"/> this Port; And becauſe we have had experience that the carriage of that ſort of people is ridiculous and is capable to bring diſhonour to our Nation, beſides other inconveniences that may redound to them in particular, and to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation in general.</p>
                  <p>We therefore will and require you to give a ſtop to the ſaid <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> from proceeding any further in their journey, either to <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople</hi> or the preſent Court of the Grand Signior or to any other place where our Authority extends, Shipping them away either di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly for England or any other parts where they ſhall chuſe to Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barque. And we do herely require all Officers and Members of the Factory, and Maſters and Officers of Ships to be ayding and Aſſiſting to you herein, and for ſo doing this ſhall be your Warrent.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Winchelſe.</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Given under our Hand and Seal at our Court at</hi> Pera <hi>at</hi> Conſtantinople <date>
                           <hi>the 19. day of</hi> July <hi>1661.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer>For our Loving Friend <hi>Anthony Iſacſon</hi> Eſquire, Conſul for the Engliſh Nation in <hi>Smyrna by his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies Command, Paul Kecaut</hi> Secretary.</trailer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>And they ſent a <hi>Turks</hi> Janneſary together with a <hi>Drugger</hi>-man the Conſuls Officer and <hi>Hamalls</hi> (Porters) to our lodging, and ſent us away as Priſoners.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>To the Lord Ambaſſadour (ſo called) and to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation in <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> and <hi>Smyrna.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Friend,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I am honeſtly perſwaded, <hi>viz.</hi> If that the Nobility of thy underſtanding were not vailed or darkned with preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, ſo that thou hadſt a perfect underſtanding of what thou haſt done, and if it were to do again it would be a hard thing for thee then to do the ſame, wherefore blame me not, if I tell thee in truth and plainneſs, ſaying, Behold how thou haſt turned thy hand againſt the juſt Lord, and ſet thy ſelf alſo againſt his Work, his Truth and People, and the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:54583:7"/> everlaſting, terrible God that lives for ever, (in whoſe hand thy breath is) he will certainly plead with thee for the ſame, [yea and with them alſo who with one conſent have joynd together with thee herein,] who are but a man that ſhall die and come to judgement, as its appointed for all men, and lo God hath given thee a day of viſitation, of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, but behold how thou haſt put the ſame far away from thee; and he that liveth for ever, ſo far hath tryed thee (together with the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation in <hi>Aſia</hi>) in thy place, of of Authority and Judicature, in giving thee alſo a plain and certain warning, by my hand through me. [concerning ſomewhat of the work and counſel of the <hi>Everlaſting Light,</hi> who is the Living and true God, and Father of all Truth over all bleſſed for ever <hi>Amen</hi>] before thou didſt intermeddle or proceed either to the right hand or to the left, to the end that thou might take heed, and beware of being inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal in ſtopping the work and ſervice of the Everlaſting; And lo thou haſt rejected and made light of the ſame (as doth appear) and turned thy hand againſt the Juſt, the Harmleſs and Innocent and guiltleſs, and alſo reproached the Living God, inaſmuch as the ſame is done to his Friends and Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers that have drawn ſo near thee, in peace, good will and uprightneſs of heart, and in love unfained without ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ends but with its denyal [according to the commandment of our Lord and Maſter, even Chriſt <hi>The light of the World (which lighteth every man that cometh into the World)</hi> in the work and ſervice of him, who is the Lord God of Judgement, with our pretious life alſo in our hand have we thus come, not loving our lives to the death for his Names ſake, for his Peoples ſake, for his Goſpels ſake, who freely laid down his pretious life for us, (leaving us an example) who came not in our own name, will or time, but have herein forſaken Country, Kindred and Fathers Houſe, Wife and Children and what elſe [our God that liveth for ever knoweth right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well] as our Fathers of old did, God knoweth the upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our hearts alſo, concerning this and much more, which for the Truths ſake might be declared, but at this time it is not convenient, and our meſſage (which from man we received not) of life and ſalvation, was and is, to give a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:54583:7"/> certain ſound <hi>of the great and mighty day of the Lord at hand,</hi> and alſo of the ſame life of the holy Prophets, and Apoſtles of Chriſt the <hi>Lord of life</hi> thats ariſen from the dead, with his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving health in the midſt of us, to the Nations that are invol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in thick darkneſs, and wallowing in obſcurity to awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken them, and alſo that they may aſſuredly know, that the mighty, terrible and glorious, and dreadful day of the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal God is come and at hand, and that the ſame hath alſo begun to dawn and to ſpread forth its ſhining beams of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal brightneſs in the <hi>North</hi> parts of the World, even in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> firſt, the which is manifeſting it ſelf, and ſhining forth over all Nations, to the condemnation and deſtruction of wickedneſs, and alſo to the Juſtification and Salvation of the Righteous which of the Lord is to turn the ſons of men from ungodlineſs, now after this long night of Apoſtacy, and alſo as it were to awaken the eternal <hi>Light</hi> of our Lord Jeſus) which is the witneſs of God in every conſcience, (yea and to anſwer the ſame (in all men) which is to guide Nations, the Sons and Daughters of men into all truth, againſt which they have rebelled, and from the ſame they are fallen by tranſgreſſion; And behold the Lord God that lives for ever, as in the ancient dayes is doing this and much more, and accompliſhing his own work, not according to mans way, will or time in theſe latter dayes, but as in the dayes of old, is he provoking of Nations to jealouſie to anger, and to wrath by thoſe which are not a people, he is provoking them to anger, and to wrath with a fooliſh Nation, foraſmuch as they have provoked him the everlaſting Lord of Heaven and Earth, to anger with their vanities, for ſaith the Lord, <hi>a fire is kindled in mine anger, and it ſhall burn unto the loweſt hell,</hi> it ſhall conſume the Earth with her increaſe, and ſet on fire the foundations of the Mountains.</p>
                  <p>Liſten ye great Mountains, and inhabitants of the Earth, what will become of you? where will you hide or ſly when your foundations is ſet on fire? wherefore give ear ye lofty trees, and ſtrong oaks, the Lords controverſie is with you, for ſaith he, <hi>A fire is kindled in mine anger, which will burn un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the loweſt Hell</hi> (mark that) <hi>I will heap miſchiefs upon them, I will ſpend mine Arrows upon them, they ſhall be burnt with hung<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:54583:8"/> and deſtroyed with burning heat &amp; bitter deſtruction.</hi> And friend as ſure as God hath given thee breath, know, that ſo ſure are we his Servants and Meſſengers freely given up into his hand to ſuffer his Will and Pleaſure and to do the ſame <hi>in Earth, as it is in Heaven</hi> (as thou thy ſelf prayeſt, but it would be well if thy actions did not ſpeak the contrary as certainly they do concerning this matter.</p>
                  <p>And behold the time will certainly come to paſs that the true witneſs of the Everlaſting <hi>Light</hi> in thy Conſcience will anſwer to thy underſtanding, that we are men of truth, fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God, and ſent of him (and not of or by man) whom thou haſt ſo reproached and defied, together with many more; Alas poor man I pitty thee, and as for my part I am honeſtly perſwaded, that <hi>King Charles,</hi> whom thou calls <hi>Lord and Maſter,</hi> would not have given forth ſuch a ridiculous, vile and reproachful Sentence againſt the guiltleſs, an inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent harmleſs people, as thou haſt done under thy hand and ſeal, peradventure in thy haſt (in a ſtrange Land) how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ever we pray the Lord, that the ſame may not be laid to thy charge (when thou haſt moſt need of mercy, if happily repentance unto life thou may witneſs, and albeit we may freely forgive thee by what we do or may ſuffer becauſe of thee, yet we know that the Lord will not hold you guiltleſs, after ſo clear a warning (from his mouth that liveth for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver) as you have had in your day, that are guilty in the ſame thing, and God Almighty will be clear of thee and ſo alſo will his Servant, if in your ſins you dye; and therefore behold I yet ceaſe not to cry, <hi>Repent, Repent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And ſeeing that the Everlaſting Lord <hi>and King of Eternal Life,</hi> laid a neceſſity on me more eſpecially to preform this ſervice (if <hi>Sathan</hi> hindred not) and to try thee alſo, and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation together in <hi>Aſia</hi> concerning the ſame for your good, and not otherwiſe, but behold how you have joyned together with one conſent to reject and defie the ſame meſſage of life and ſalvation, through letting up the dark ſpirit of prejudice and evil ſurmiſings againſt the Lord, the Innocent and guiltleſs, and thus (to your greater con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation have you been permitted by the everlaſting God, ſo far to have your own hearts deſire, and to expell the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:54583:8"/> Friends and Meſſengers of Chriſt out of your Coaſts or Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, once and again, and not only ſo, but as much as in you concerns, not to ſuffer them to come within the extent of your Authority, in the <hi>Turks</hi> Dominion, in which you are as ſaith the <hi>Warrant;</hi> but will you bear with me if I queſtion with you, ſaying, <hi>what are they contrary to all men?</hi> as a rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious Generation ſaid to the holy Apoſtles, <hi>And what do they bear Teſtimony, not for, but againſt the World, becauſe the deeds thereof are evil,</hi> and can they not <hi>neither receive the Honour and Glory of it, nor give the ſame to any man,</hi> according to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat example of their <hi>Lord and Maſter the life of man,</hi> the true Chriſt, for which end Chriſt is come in the fleſh, as he did many hundred years ſince, who hath by his grace of life manifeſt in us freely redeemed us from the ſame vanities and pollutions which we witneſs (and teſtifie againſt in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
                  <p>And will you blame me if I ſay, what are not you of the ſame generation, as <hi>Job</hi> ſaw <hi>rebel againſt the Light who know not the wayes thereof, neither abide in the paths thereof, Job.</hi> 24.13. <hi>and Job.</hi> 21. Alas poor men, are you the men alſo that are without a good and noble underſtanding, <hi>and are wiſe to do evil, and hate to be reformed,</hi> to diſcern between the pretious and the vile; Alas for you, yea woe and alas for you, what have ye done? cannot you ſmite upon your thigh, and ſay on this wiſe, how ſhall we account with the Lord of life, of eternity for theſe things and much more, when his mighty hand, and the weight thereof you feel heavy upon your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences in the day that ſhall burn as an Oven, according to the Propheſie of the Eternal Spirit by <hi>Mallachi, Mal.</hi> 3.</p>
                  <p>Behold and know ye, O ye great men of the Earth, ye high Mountains, Strong Oakes and lofty Trees, this I with a clean mind declare unto you, if I be no more, <hi>(viz.)</hi> that our Conſciences are clear in the ſight of God, that lives for ever, who with a pure eternal eye, perfectly beholds the intents and uprightneſs of our hearts (though hid from you) concerning this ſervice, and the living teſtimony of life an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth in us to the ſame, and therefore have I bouldneſs in the Truth to ſtand, and alſo to write on this wiſe; And again I ſay, <hi>we are clear from the guilt which remains upon your
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:54583:9"/> Conſciences.</hi> And furthermore know ye that our ſervice is ſo far accepted and we are alſo clear of the ſame in and by Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>our Lord and Maſter,</hi> who moved us hereunto, and ſent us freely to and among you in the <hi>Turks</hi> Borders and Dominion, the which by your actions its manifeſt ye would have ſtand, but God Almighty hath otherwiſe deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, with a notwithſtanding, and ſurely it would be well with you could you witneſs and ſavour the anſwer of a good Conſcience, the which in the truth verily and certainly we do, in the ſight of God concerning this our ſervice (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you believe the ſame or not) its even ſo; And again I ſay we are clear of your guilt and condemnation, before the Lord God of Judgement, the Judge of all; and be it known unto you that he who ſent us is true, whoſe witneſſes we are; Albeit ſome of you (as the ſame Generation in the daies of old, contemptuouſly and maliciouſly ſaid to him, <hi>that he was mad and had a devil</hi> and what elſe, yet we have in the Lord held faſt our integritie in the Truth, in Life and Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to confeſs him before men, and bear his reproaches in the fellowſhip of his Sufferings, following his harmleſs and compleat example, as the Sons of God in the midſt of a crooked and perverſe Generation, unto which we are called, and are his living witneſſes and teſtifie of his undefiled life manifeſt in us, and that he alſo is ariſen from the dead and <hi>liveth for ever</hi> in the everlaſting <hi>Light,</hi> the which is your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation and not ſalvation (whatſoever you profeſs in words) whilſt you are found ſetting your ſelves againſt his appearance (now in this ſecond coming <hi>a quickning ſpirit</hi> [who is the Lord from Heaven] <hi>without ſin unto ſalvation</hi> in his Friends and Meſſengers) as who hath drawn ſo near you, with his viſitation of Salvation in ſuch clouds of witneſſes, in and with his mighty pure power of holineſs, yet with them eyes (that are Adulterated from his undefiled life, and truth) which cannot ceaſe from ſin (with which you ſee) therewith cannot you behold him who is and is to be glorified in his Saints, and alſo admired in all them that believe, who will certainly render venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance (as ſaith the Holy Scripture) not onely on them that know not God, but alſo on them that obey not
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:54583:9"/> the Goſpel of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, the <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Life</hi> of men who taſted death for every man, and as certain he lighteth every man that cometh into the World, to the end that all men in him who is the <hi>Light</hi> might believe and be ſaved (by the <hi>Light,</hi> who is the Author of Eternal Salvation) not onely from ſin which worketh guilt and condemnation, but alſo from the wrath to come, but wo will be to them that not onely withſtand his Appearance, his Truth and People (who are not according, but contrary to the World, its Wayes, Worſhips, Honours and Glory, Traditions and Luſts, and herein neither enter your ſelves) but alſo as much as in them is hinder others, who are as it were ready to enter, from going in; but behold <hi>Publicant, Harlots</hi> are, and come to be converted, and ſo to enter the Kingdom, whileſt men of high degree themſelves are ſhut out; And will you bear with me if I ask you, ſaying, Have you been at all careful, and not forgetful to entertain ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers? Or have you not wilfully and deſpitefully ſhut the ſame out of your remembrance? And how have you obeyed the perfect Doctrine of the Goſpel of God? But what hath not Chriſt in his Friends, in his Lambs and Meſſengers, been as Strangers and Pilgrims? Yea hath not he been as a Priſoner and Captive, deſpiſed in and among you, but how at all have you viſited him, or entertained him, that beareth the iniquity and liveth for ever? He right well knoweth, and in the day of God ſo ſhall you, and it may be well if the ſame will appear to your juſtification; Poor men my heart pitieth you, woe and alaſs for you, but the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, not to your juſtification do we witneſs fulfilled; And what if I ſay your unchriſtian-like dealing againſt us, the ſame turns to us for a Teſtimony [albeit, we rejoyce not, as your reward will be evil unto your ſelves, but mourn over you] and if this we did not witneſſe in our integrity, ſure of all men moſt miſerable ſhould we be, and as he ſaith, who is the <hi>Reſurrection and the Life</hi> (viz) <hi>If they have perſecuted me, they alſo will perſecute you; if they had kept my ſayings, they would keep yours alſo, but theſe things will they do unto you</hi> (why) <hi>becauſe they know not him that ſent me,</hi> ſaith <hi>Jeſus, John</hi> 15. And have ye not read theſe ſayings, <hi>Now I tell you before it
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:54583:10"/> come to paſs, that when it is come to paſs you might believe that I am he; Verily, verily, he that receiveth whomſoever I ſend, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth me, and he that receiveth me, receiveth him that ſent me, John</hi> 13. But conſider, have you received him, or do you know what is the thing, or whom you have rejected and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in what you have done to them whom he hath aſſuredly ſent, whether you can believe the ſame or not; And do you not know that he ſaith on this wiſe, <hi>He that heareth you, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth me, and he that deſpiſeth you, deſpiſeth me, and he that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſeth me, deſpiſeth him that ſent me, Luke</hi> 10.16. And do you think it had not been better your hand had been laid upon your month, and to have manifeſted ſilence in the fear of the Lord, rather then to have proceeded ſo far as this to your own hurt? Woe and alas for you, how can you truly ſay to the contrary in the Day of God? and is it not your ſins and your iniquities which keeps back <hi>good things from you?</hi> And can you ſay that the words of our Living Teſtimony have been at any time againſt any thing thats of the nature of God thats Equitable and Juſt? And what, muſt all your ſtrength and wiſdom with what elſe you have, be ſtirred up to keep up the ſtrong holds of darkneſs, its Works and Fruits, even of the man of ſin, and <hi>Satans</hi> Kingdom, is it not even ſo? Bear with me if I ask you, what ye think of ſuch that were to depart from the preſence of the King of Eternal life into everlaſting fire, with the Devil and his Angels, who viſited no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Chriſt though ſick and in priſon, and when he was a ſtranger and naked took him not in, neither cloathed him, nor nouriſhed him with either meat or drink, when hungry and thirſty, cold and naked, but bowels of compaſſion was ſhut up, ſuch took him not in (nay there is no room for the Babe of Glory in the Inn, but a Manger where the beaſts feed over him, there the Virgins firſt born muſt lie) Oh that any of you having ears to hear may hear; but what think you will be the portion of ſuch that not onely deaſe not to do ſuch things to him in his Members, but alſo ſpeak all manner of evil againſt him, and are not content there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, but he muſt be baniſhed as a Rogue or Vaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bond out of their Coaſts and Borders, whoſe carriage alſo muſt be as it is deemed and termed, <hi>Ridiculous, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:54583:10"/> capable to bring diſhonour to a Nation</hi> (becauſe his Kingdom, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Glory is not of this World) as ſome one ſaith, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing poſſeſſed with fear, even as they were, who ſaid of him whom the Nations abhoreth, <hi>(viz.) If we let him thus alone, all men will believe on him, and the</hi> Romans <hi>will come and take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way our Place and Nation;</hi> And ſo had they not reſpect to their perſons and places, and outward vain Honour and Glory of their Nation (which was and is to be defaced and brought into contempt) more then to Chriſt the <hi>Light,</hi> and ſaving Truth of all Nations, and true Honour thereof, and therefore juſtly condemned, and there houſes left deſolate, as the Holy Scriptures witneſſeth; but will you blame me, yet if I ask you ſaying, What will you condemn a hard-hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Generation, and juſtifie your ſelves, whileſt you are walking in the ſteps, and doing the ſame things (like the <hi>Gaderenes</hi> and unbelieving Jews in the dayes of Chriſt) put it not far from you, its even ſo whether you hear or forbear, wherefore out of your Coaſts and Borders and elſe where the extent of your Authority or Dominion doth reach or extend, muſt he (the Lamb) be expelled or baniſhed. Woe and alas for you, woe and alas for you, that know not what you do, who ſhall bewail you, when no hiding place will be found from his Eternal Light and Everlaſting Wrath to hide? Behold whether you hear or forbear how the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of Truth is fulfilled, not to your juſtification, as ſaith Chriſt our Lord and Maſter <hi>(viz.) in as much as ye did it not</hi> (Concerning Receiving, Viſiting, and Communicating) <hi>to one of the leaſt of theſe, ye did it not unto me, Mat.</hi> 23. and theſe ſhall go into <hi>Everlaſting puniſhment, but the Righteous into Life Eternal,</hi> whom you have wilfully rejected and unjuſtly condemned, and think not that this is to juſtifie our ſelves, but the Grace of God which is our life and ſtrength, which of a truth we have gladly received, and its ſet up in our Hearts, otherwiſe at this day we had not been (but Glory, Bleſſing and Salvation to the Lord our God over all, <hi>Amen.</hi>)</p>
                  <p>And will you bear with me yet a little, if I proceed to que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry what is the Crimes that are or tend to be ſo <hi>Rediculous,</hi> thats ſo capable to bring diſhonour to the Nation; Was not
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:54583:11"/> 
                     <hi>Nicodemus</hi> [a maſter in <hi>Iſrael</hi>] ſomewhat Noble, when he would not have the Law to judge a man before it hear him? <hi>Doth our Law Judge a man before it hear him,</hi> ſaith he, and ſaith King <hi>AGRIPPA, I would hear the man my ſelf,</hi> and its well known what he was (a <hi>Heathen</hi> termed) who was ſo Noble in ſuch a Matter, as to hear the Accuſed as well as the Accuſers.</p>
                  <p>And if thou O <hi>Ambaſsador</hi> (for <hi>King Charles</hi> of Great <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane</hi> in the <hi>Turks</hi> Dominion) hadeſt manifeſted the Nobility of a good underſtanding, ſo Nobly in the firſt place, before ſuch a haſty ſentence was given forth under thy Hand and Seal, by thee, to have ſuffered us to come and appeared be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee, to the end that thou mighteſt have enquired ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly into the Nature and Ground of the Matter, as a man of God in the place of Judicature, and ſo according as thou hadſt found us either Clear or Guilty of unjuſt Crimes (which indeed are <hi>Ridiculous, and tends to the Diſhonour &amp; Deſtructiveneſs of a Kingdom or Nation,</hi>) &amp; then to have clered thy Conſcience, in laying the Sword in its due place, as a terror to evil doers, and not upon the head of the Innocent and Guiltleſs, to whom he that bears the Sword of the Righteouſneſs as a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of God, ſhould be a praiſe, and our Bodies would alſo have been ready either to do or ſuffer accordingly; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, herein thou alſo haſt been wanting, and the Guiltleſs Cauſe thou haſt not pleaded, but contrariwiſe condemned the ſame; and hereby they have ſuffered the more, but the reproaches of Chriſt they eſteem as great Riches, though accounted they be even as the vileſt off ſcouring of all things; yet what is their Ridiculous Crimes, what is it becauſe they are ſcornfully called <hi>Quakers,</hi> or becauſe they are the <hi>Elect of God,</hi> Redeemed from a vain Converſation, and conform not to the Vanities, Traditions, Luſts and Cuſtoms of the World, which are not of the Father of all Truth? or is it becauſe all men ſpeak not well but evil of them, and ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate them from their Company, as Chriſt Propheſied ſhould befal them? <hi>Luke</hi> 6.22. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.22. or is it becauſe they cannot <hi>Swear at all,</hi> neither Lye nor Diſſemble, but ſpeak the truth from the heart to every man in plainneſſe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſpect of Perſons, Nations or Places? or is it becauſe for Conſcience ſake (and not in any evil ſurmiſing, or contempt
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:54583:11"/> to any mans perſon) they honeſtly wear their Hats, as the reſt of their plain and uſeful Garments, and cannot receive, neither give the honour thats beneath the Son with flatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Titles, either to themſelves or to any man, which is not contrary, but according to the Perfect and Compleat Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Chriſt their Lord and Maſter, and Captain of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, who receives not honour from man, and ſaith, <hi>How can you believe, which receive honour one of another,</hi> Mat. 5:</p>
                  <p>But I demand as a Chriſtian, in truth and indeed, as a free born <hi>Engliſh</hi> man, yet further, what is the evil (theſe that are ſo contrary to the World, its Friendſhip Honour and Glory) that they have at all done? Or what are they guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of, that they are deemed ſo <hi>Ridiculous;</hi> and ſo capable to bring Diſhonour to a Nation? (who ſhall become a bleſſing to all Nations, with a notwithſtanding this and that which letteth, thats to be taken out of the way) What muſt peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple believe Accuſations to be true, without inſtancing or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Cauſe manifeſt to their underſtandings, becauſe its the pleaſure of men of high degree, to ſay they are ſo, and ſo, is this ſufficient to ſtand before the God of Judgement, and good men of underſtanding? who have they been chargea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble unto, or who have they defrauded? or have they eaten any mans bread for nought? or wherein is their carriage <hi>Ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous?</hi> or what is any manner of their Crimes, or Behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, or Deportment, otherwiſe then Peace and Love that worketh no ill to its neighbour, but good will to all men, in Truth and Uprightneſs, Temperence and Sobriety, in Life and Converſation? (but whats the matter with the <hi>Sons of men,</hi> that they ſo burthen themſelves with the <hi>Sons of Truth,</hi> and blameleſs Servants of the Living God, who do all things well in the <hi>Light,</hi> through Chriſt the <hi>light</hi> that ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eneth them) let the Lords Witneſs, the <hi>light</hi> in your Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences ariſe to anſwer, either to your Juſtification or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation. O ye men of <hi>England</hi> in <hi>Aſia,</hi> can you juſtly charge any evil againſt them, let the ſame come forth and be manifeſt to the whole VVorld, if Equity and Truth be on your ſide, but if the ſavory Fruits of the Life of Eternal Righteouſneſſe, in ſound Doctrine, with wholeſom Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:54583:12"/> that corrupteth not good manners, with long-ſuffering, meekneſs and gentleneſs of Chriſt brought forth by them <hi>who ſhine as lights in the world</hi> (being redeemed from the vanities and evils thereof) if theſe be the fruits and manners, or things ye call <hi>evil,</hi> ſurely in ſo doing the ſame tends not to your juſtification; and are theſe the <hi>Ridiculous</hi> Crimes that will bring <hi>diſhonour to a Nation,</hi> what will equity, truth and uprightneſs, and plainneſs of a heart, temperance, innocency and ſobriety, with ſavoury and wholeſome Communications, without guile, fraud or deceit in life and good converſation doing the will of God from the heart in his fear and reverence, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> theſe the things that are deemed ſo <hi>Ridiculous</hi> and capable to bring Diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to the <hi>Nation,</hi> to the <hi>King</hi> or his juſt <hi>Government,</hi> or is it not the contrary, even the hurtful luſts which men fulfil and walk after, from whence wars and fightings ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, together with evil Surmiſings, Strife, and Debate, and Violence, and Spoile, with flatterings and guile ariſeth, double-mindedneſs, revealings pride of life and hypocriſie, al ariſing from one and the ſame ground of iniquity in the Sons of men, from whence alſo cometh ſo much Waſting, Devouring and conſuming the good Bleſſings and Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God upon the ungodlineſs and hurtful luſts, that wars againſt the Pretious and Immortal Soul, and are not only hurtful and deſtructive to a man, to his Body, Soul, Mind and Spirit, but alſo to the greeving, and provoking, and wounding of the Juſt, Eternal Lord God of Heaven and Earth, and ſo becomes deſtructive alſo to a Family, to a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to a Kingdom and Nation.</p>
                  <p>And what are not theſe and ſuch like, the noyſom and unſavoury Fruits (which is a ſhame to Chriſtianity and ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly contrary to the moſt Wiſe, Gentle, Temperate Life of the Lord Jeſus and his Saints upon Earth) ſo frequently by the Apoſtate Chriſtians, and Chriſtians by name only, brought forth day by day, among the <hi>Turks,</hi> who excel many of them in uprightneſs, ſteadfaſtneſs and temperance in things civil, and in matters of communications and deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing between man and man, to your condemnation, who are guilty and ſo below them herein, ſo that an ill ſavour
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:54583:12"/> hath aſcended up to the Lord, from the unwholeſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation of the Chriſtians by name and words out of the true Chriſtians ſavoury, meek, gentle, long-ſuffering life, bringing forth contrary and unſavoury fruits, and what are not theſe the things that is <hi>Ridiculous,</hi> and alſo capable to bring diſhonour to a <hi>Nation,</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>King</hi> and to their own bodies and ſouls oppreſſion [men of clear underſtanding will not reject but conſent and adhere to my Teſtimony] by reaſon of ſuch diſhonourable fruits abounding in a ſtrange Land, among the Nations of men, and thereby give occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to them called <hi>Turks, Heathens, Jews</hi> and <hi>Infidels,</hi> and what others among you, not to win them to the moſt holy Faith of Gods elect, but contrariwiſe to abide in their brutiſhneſs, hardneſs of heart and infidelity, and unbelief, and not only ſo, but alſo to blaſpheme and diſhonour the Lord God of <hi>Eternal Life</hi> and his <hi>Worthy Name,</hi> by which ye are called, and alſo to reject and defie both you and your Religion, and Chriſtianity in the generall.</p>
                  <p>Oh how often my very heart hath been grieved and my ſoul oppreſſed and wounded in me many a time, from time to time, yea over the men of my own Nation have I wept, and mourned, [whilſt they have magnified themſelves in the pleaſures of unrighteouſneſs, againſt their own ſouls, and the people of the Lord of hoſts,] my God knoweth becauſe of theſe things: And oh our Souls hath been wounded, grieved and vexed from time to time, and preſſed down in us day by day even as truly as the ſoul of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Lot</hi> was in <hi>Sodom,</hi> becauſe of the unſavoury and unfruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful words and works of darkneſs, brought forth by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate Chriſtians of all ſorts, among the <hi>Turks;</hi> Oh the pride of life, Oh the vanities, Oh the exceſs and ſuperfluites of noughtineſs abounding together with flattery, deceit and double-mindedneſs that abounds and ſuperabounds, among and over the <hi>falſe Chriſtians,</hi> which keeps back the Heavenly diſtillings of the early and latter rain from on high, that the ſame deſends not to reach to the lower parts of the Earth, where the poor priſoners of hope and exiled captives are ſhut up, but have any of you an ear to hear, or eyes to ſee whats the matter that hinders, Stops the bleſſings of eternity, by
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:54583:13"/> reſiſting that which is holy (which checks and reproves for ſin, evil and vanity) in your ſelves and others, the ſame good thing is freely given of God, to guide you and all men into all truth, and from the contrary in which the <hi>falſe Chriſtians</hi> excels the <hi>Turks,</hi> even in unrighteouſneſs, and I am as it were conſtrained to write on this wiſe, to their ſhame, yet in love if happily the ſame may tend to their Salvation, from the contrary, effect and ground of oppreſſion with its fruits, ſo that they hereby have provoked the Eternal God of mercy and judgement not a little, and have cauſed his anger to wax hot, and to burn like a conſuming fire againſt the root and ground of iniquity raigning in and over the Sons and Daughters of men, and his wrath and ſore diſpleaſure from Heaven, in the eternal Light is revealed againſt the ſame, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the veſſels of wrath fitted for deſtruction, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of you may feel the ſame, not to your juſtification or ſalvation, who have been ſuch an ill ſavour to the Lord, and his Friends, and crucifie his meek, ſweet and temperate life even of the <hi>Lamb,</hi> the <hi>Light</hi> our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, day by day, as if every day were a day of ſlaughter, ſo that the noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome corrupt fruits which are not meet for repentance, are a noy ſome ſmell even among the <hi>Turks</hi> as I have truly ſaid, and many of you will find it ſo in one day, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God eternal time after time hath not been wanting with viſitations in viſiting you both with judgemens and mercies, yet may it not be ſaid for all this, will they not learn righteouſneſs, but rather wax worſe and worſe, and are ready to ſay, <hi>who ſhall reprove or be Lord over us,</hi> and to the moſt high as them that rebel againſt the <hi>Light</hi> did, ſaying, <hi>depart from us, for we deſire not the knowledge of thy wayes</hi> but to take pleaſure, not in the Truth but in unrighteouſnes, whoſe reward muſt be according to the unfruitful works of darkneſs, and God Almighty may yet plead with you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning theſe things, and happily to try you, yet more Meſſengers of Righteouſneſs may he ſend to viſit you [to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the <hi>Jews, Turks and Heathens</hi>] that if happily your end may be peace and not otherwiſe, which we chiefly ſeek and travel in love and good will for the ſame (whether you will hear or forbear) either to your eternal ſalvation or condemnation.</p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:54583:13"/>
                  <p>But will you not count me your Enemy and deſpiſe me, If I in the truth tell you the truth, ſaying, miſery and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, oppreſſion with hard-heartedneſſe is yet in your wayes, take heed and beware leaſt the ſame ariſe up ſo high, and at laſt overcome you to eternal perdition, and if I ſhould teſtifie, ſaying, <hi>This is a certain warning from the hand of God that liveth for ever:</hi> I right well know you can hardly believe the words of my Living teſtimony, but I perfectly know from what Spirit and ground they are brought forth, and I am well ſatisfied in the life that now is, and was, and ſhall for ever be one and the ſame which is Unchangable, Immortal, Inviſible, Eternal, without variableneſs or ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of turning in the leaſt degree into any contrariaty from its own pure nature or property, and clear ſubſtance of its undefiled nature of true Light and Life, which never fadeth away, in which I reſt, and in the ſame my living ſoul magnifieth the living inviſible God of immortality and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life, to whom be living endleſs praiſes, with eternal Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion over all this and that which letteth (which is to be taken out of the way) now and for ever <hi>as in the beginning</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And for ſo much as you have ſo far made light of the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of the good day of your viſitation of ſalvation, now the day light of the morning is begun to dawn over the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions (the dark night of Apoſtacy, ſince the Holy Apoſtles dayes being ſo far ſpent) the clouds of obſcurity and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitful works of the night of darkn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſs being made manifeſt by the <hi>Light</hi> of <hi>Eternity,</hi> and brought to the ſame for judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and condemnation, but behold how you have been found Defying, Rejecting, Abhorring and Perſecuting the Prophets, and Meſſengers, and People of the true and living God, who ſent us not in our own name, will or time, to prove you and to warn you, and to preach repentance, and reformation, and reconciliation to God among you in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia,</hi> as in other parts of the World, not in your own way or wiſdome that is not from above but from beneath, of the World, who have been permitted ſo far as to ſtop us in the work of our God to your own hurt, and what if I ſhould ſay on this wiſe, <hi>Let the Lord require the ſame at your hands</hi> and of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:54583:14"/> that Generation, that is under the line of unrighteouſneſs, that runs paralel through the unbelieving, wrathful, perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting nature, even from <hi>Cain</hi> unto this preſent day, who are uncircumcized in heart and ears, and ſtifnecked, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies reſiſting the holy Ghoſt as did your Fathers, as the holy man who was filled with the Holy Ghoſt, ſaith <hi>Acts</hi> 7. But I have prayed that what you have done, may not be laid to your Charge, who know not what you do, ye know I ſpeak truth, and the Light of Chriſt in you will anſwer me, in the day of God, whether yet you hear or forbear, I am and ſhall be clear, albeit as much as in you is ye have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to ſtop and hinder the work of the everlaſting God, and his glorious truth from ſpreading, yet the Truth (the Light that is eternal) the ſame <hi>which lighteeth every man that cometh into the World,</hi> I ſay with a notwithſtanding, ſhall it break forth and ſhine perfectly bright, and ſpread its ſame, glory, and eternal excellency, through and over all Nations, and proſper according to the moſt wiſe Decree, and eternal Counſel of the everlaſting Lord the Light and King of eternal life, and the ſame ſhall awaken and anſwer the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal witneſs that is juſt in every Conſcience, whether <hi>Turks, Jews, Chriſtians</hi> or <hi>Heathens,</hi> under what name or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination ſoever they be called: And behold this my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit prophecieth <hi>(viz.) that with them eyes you now may ſee with ſhall you never behold the ſame, neither the Goodneſs, Riches, Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings and Mercies which the everlaſting Light hath in ſtore to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence among and over the Nations of men that come to fear him and his goodneſſe, and alſo turn from ungodlineſſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And behold furthermore I declare that your evil intents and works of darkneſſe, what if I ſay the ſame ſhall work to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether for our good unto eternal life and peace, and ſo turn to us for a teſtimony, as it doth not to your juſtification, but contrariwiſe, yet our prayer is for you that hate us without a cauſe, but the time may come, and it haſteneth, <hi>that you may wiſh you had never been born to have ſeen this Age and Generation,</hi> whilſt we cry wo and alas for you, in the day in which the burthenſom ſtone though little (as cut out of the Mountain without hands) it is known and the Nations that burthen themſelves with it ſhall be cut in pieces, and grownd
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:54583:14"/> to powder on whom it falls <hi>(whoſe light is like unto a ſtone moſt pretious clear as Chryſtal)</hi> according to the propheſie of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Spirit of holineſs, and verily the mercy and goodneſs and knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Jeſus Chriſt, the ſame ſhall fill the Earth and abundantly ſtream forth, and ſpread its virtue and excellent power over all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and flow plentifully even to the ends and uttermoſt parts of the Earth from Sea to Sea and to the utmoſt extent or circumference of its bounds; the Lord, the Lord of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in his own life, and by the Almightineſſe of his own Arm thats revealed and manifeſt in the midſt of his poor afflicted and deſpiſed, yet honourable people, againſt whom you have magnified your ſelves to your own hurt, in and by whom, without viſible weapons of war, will he even our Lord perform the ſame and much more, and many both on the right hand and on the left ſhall break forth as a mighty flood, or as the Stars of the Firmament of the power of the everlaſting Light, and many ſhall fear and tremble, becauſe of the abundance of peace and truth, that is, and is yet to be revealed even in them that turn from ungodlineſſe to the Light of the Lord who enlighteneth the poor, and deceitful mans eyes, the Lord enlightneth both their eyes ſaith the wiſe man, and the poor man is guided in obedience to the ſame light which juſtifieth him, and condemneth the deceitful man that hates it, <hi>Prov.</hi> 29. ſo he that doth evil hateth the Light which is not Salvation but Condemnation to the evil doer, as Chriſt ſaith, <hi>John the</hi> 3d. And bleſſed ſhall the man be that believeth in, and obeyeth the Light of the Lord ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt in him, to guide him into all Truth from all the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, and the Nations ſhall be aſnamed and confounded be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of all the goodneſs that the eternal God of Judgement will perform unto, and in the bleſſed and beloved obedient Seed of his bowels, thats to be gathered from the four winds and ends of the Earth where they have been (in the dark night of Apoſtacy) ſcattered.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore with my ſingle voice behold I cry unto you, yet by the ſame Eternal Spirit of Life and Propheſie, take heed and beware leaſt that therefore come upon you, which is ſpoken of in the Prophets, ſaying, <hi>Behold ye diſpiſers and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:54583:15"/> Wonder, and Periſh, the Lord is working a work in your dayes, which you will in no wiſe believe, though a man declare it unto you;</hi> and whether you hear or forbear, the Scripture do I witneſs fulfilled in me, in the anſwer of a Good Conſcience, according to the Compleat and Perfect Example of my Lord and Maſter, whom I Fear and follow, and ſerve, in the Fellowſhip of his Reproaches &amp; Sufferings in the Goſpel Life and Peace, <hi>viz.</hi> The Lord God hath opened mine ear, (Bleſſed be his Glory Amen) and I was not Rebellious a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, neither turned away back; I gave my back to the ſmiter, and my check to them that plucked off the Hair; I hid not my face from ſhame and ſpitting, my God knoweth right well, in obedience to his will the ſame is done, being called to the Fellowſhip of the ſame Sufferings and Glory of Gods Lamb, and to indure the contradictions of ungodly ſinners, as he did, yea, the Lord God will help me, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhall I not be confounded; thou haſt made my face like a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>line, and I know that I ſhall not be aſhamed, he is near that juſtifieth, who ſhall contend with me?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Behold all ye that kindle a fire, and compaſs your ſelves about with ſparks of your own kindling, walk in the light of your fire, and in the ſparks that ye have kindled, this ſhall ye have of my hand, ye ſhall lie down in ſorrow.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This following was ſent in a Letter, from the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſul at <hi>Grand Caire,</hi> to an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchant in <hi>Legorne</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> concerning <hi>Henry Fell</hi> and <hi>John Stubs.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Forgot to adviſe you how that the Quakers at their departure, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down to the <hi>Marine,</hi> did throw Pamphlets about the Streets, in <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>atine, Hebrew</hi> and <hi>Arabique,</hi> which might have ſet them a burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing had they ſtayed a little longer; Therefore I beſeech you, if you hear hereafter of any ſuch people that intend to come this way, to prevent them what you can, for they may do me a great prejudice.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Rich. Bendiſh.</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Grand Caire,</hi> 
                        <date>
                           <hi>20th. Septem. 1661.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:54583:15"/>
                  <head>A Loving Viſitation, tendred to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants in <hi>Genoa,</hi> who received it not.</head>
                  <p>Friends, <hi>Read and Honeſtly conſider with the Spirit of Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for whether you will hear or forbear, this is that you may well underſtand, that in the firſt place,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>THE moſt Holy Faith of Gods Elect (without which its impoſſible to pleaſe God) its not of that Nature, to <hi>Reſpect Perſons,</hi> neither to give <hi>flattering Titles</hi> to any man, (which are of the vain inventions of vain man) but to honour, or well eſteem all men in the Truth, Fear and Reverence of God, the which is to have the Pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar and Supream Preheminence in every mans Conſcience, and ſo to rule over the whole Creation of God, that the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Bleſſing of the Inviſible and Immortal God, by Jeſus Chriſt the <hi>True Light</hi> of the world, may come upon all, in the true Seed which is ordained to <hi>bruiſe the Serpents Head,</hi> and to deſtroy the Devil and his unfruitful works of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in man, the which captivateth and defileth (and alſo is deſtructive to) the Creation, over which the true Seed is to Rule, who is the True Light which lighteth every man, and is the Way, the Life, the Truth, a manifeſtation of the ſame is in every man, in Male and in Female, it ſhines in darkneſs (in man) and the ſame would guide them out of, and from every unjuſt way, word, thought and action, yea and from all unequitableneſs, into truth and uprightneſſe, wherein the Riches of Eternal Peace and Felicity may come, and in the ſame be poſſeſſed within the heart of every particular, even in the midſt of the ſons of men, to the Glory of the Everlaſting Fountain of Life, from whence the true Property and pure nature of every good thing receiveth vertue to ſubſiſt according to the excellent and unſearchable wiſdom and decree of the Divine Subſtance or Eternal Being of the Majeſty of the Heavenly
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:54583:16"/> Power of the Everlaſting Light, who is the True and Living God over all, bleſſed for ever, Amen.</p>
                  <p>Now to the end that prejudice and evil ſurmiſings (which are not of God the Father of all Truth) may be removed out of the minds of the men of my own Nation <hi>(viz.) Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh,</hi> or any others that burthen themſelves becauſe I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not give, neither receive the honour of the world, with its Ceremonies and flattering Titles, either to my ſelf or to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man, and I am willing to teſtifie, that its not in any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to the perſons (which are the workmanſhip of the Eternal God) of the ſons of men, but for Conſcience ſake, that I uſe not the ſame as in times paſt, and becauſe I am well perſwaded in the Grace of God, and perfectly ſatisfied in the ſame meaſure in my own particular; therefore in that love which thinks no evil, I am moved to give forth ſome reaſonable and true words, to a good end as aforeſaid, which are not contrary to God, neither to the example of juſt and honourable men, nor to the Holy Scriptures of Truth, which ſaith to the True Chriſtians, <hi>If you reſpect perſons ye commit ſin, and are convinced by the Law as Tranſgreſſors,</hi> ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>James, James</hi> 2.9. <hi>And there is no reſpect of perſons with the Lord, who will judge righteouſly according to every mans work</hi> ſaith <hi>Peter,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.17. And ye ſhall do no unrighteouſneſſe in judgement, <hi>Thou ſhalt not reſpect the perſon of the poor, nor honor the perſon of the Mighty,</hi> (mark that) <hi>but in Righteouſneſſe ſhalt thou judge thy Neighbour,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>Deut.</hi> 19.15. <hi>And I ſay unto you, that for every idle word that men ſhall ſpeak, they ſhall give account thereof in the day of judgement, for by thy words thou ſhalt be juſtifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d, and by thy words thou ſhalt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, ſaith Jeſus, Mat.</hi> 12.36, 37. I teſtifie that the light of Chriſt Jeſus in every mans Conſcience, will clearly ſhew or manifeſt to mans underſtanding, what words, thoughts and intentions are juſtifiable, and what are alſo condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; wherefore my ſpirit of life is ready to ſay, Bleſſed is and ſhall the man be who ſuffereth his mind to be guided by the pure and true manifeſtation of the Eternal light, which is of the Nature of God manifeſt within, as it is written, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.19, 20. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.7. <hi>For the manifeſtation of the Spirit</hi> (which is true) <hi>is given to every man to profit withall,</hi> and they that
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:54583:16"/> profit not by the ſame, ſhall certainly receive the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable ſervants portion, not to Salvation, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe unto perdition, which is the juſt reward of them, which not onely reject the Truth and receive it not in the love of the ſame, but alſo take pleaſure in unrighteouſneſs, and ſo provoke the Lord to his Face, and defie and condemn the juſt in themſelves, and the Generation of the Righteous alſo in the General, <hi>but yee ſhall not walk in the manners of the Nations, which I caſt out before you,</hi> ſaith God to the true Seed, <hi>for they commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all theſe things, and therefore I abhorred them,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>Levit.</hi> 20. <hi>let not me I pray you reſpect the perſon of any, neither let me give flattering Titles unto men, for I know not to give flattering Titles, in ſo doing my Maker would ſoon take me away, Job</hi> 32. he will ſurely reprove you if ye ſecretly reſpect perſons, <hi>ſhall not his excellency make You afraid, Job</hi> 13. but they that are taking pleaſure in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers luſts and vanities, which maketh war againſt the Immortal ſoul, and wounds the ſpirit of the juſt, theſe are they that are of one and the ſame Nature and Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration that the holy and perfect man ſaw in his dayes (who feared God and departed from evil) <hi>which rebel againſt the light, they know not the wayes thereof, neither a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide in the paths thereof,</hi> who alſo ſay as they did to the Moſt High, <hi>depart from us, for we deſire not the knowledge of thy wayes, Job.</hi> 24.13, 14. <hi>Job</hi> 21. But God ſhall wound the Head of his Enemies, and ſpend his Arrows of Famine and Deſtruction upon ſuch as being often reproved, yet hardneth their necks, and go on ſtill in the way that is not holineſſe, ruſhing mightily into ſin and tranſgreſſion, without fear or amazement, even as the Horſe ruſheth into the Battel, and ſo greedily drink down iniquities even as the Ox drinketh water, yea and hate to be reformed, which is the greateſt evil, which hardneth their impenitent hearts the more unto perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Wo and alaſs for them that ſit in darkneſs, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſhadow of Death and Deſtruction, before their day of Viſitation finally paſs away over their heads, when
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:54583:17"/> they inexcuſably may be left to cry out in the Anguiſh and Vexation of Spirit, ſaying, <hi>How have we wilfully and rebelliouſly deſpiſed, and ſtifneckedly defyed the day of healing and ſaving health,</hi> and then ſay I, <hi>Dives</hi> his nature that fared ſumptuouſly every day in exceſs and fulneſs, ſhall ſenſibly diſcern the nature of poor <hi>Lazarus</hi> and its reward, and alſo that which is of the fleſh, the firſt birth, and the luſt thereof which is contrary to, and warreth againſt the ſpirit and its birth, and then the two ſeeds may be diſcerned the one from the other, the ſeed of God from the ſeed of the Serpent, <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abels</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and worſhip, <hi>Eſau</hi> and <hi>Jacobs</hi> nature, the <hi>prophane perſon,</hi> and the <hi>plain man,</hi> the hunting nature, and that which is obedient, quiet and dwells <hi>within,</hi> at home in his Tent; <hi>Iſaak</hi> and <hi>Iſmael,</hi> the ſeed of Bondage from beneath, and the free born from Above, the ſcoffer which is to be caſt out, &amp; the beloved Heir of the Promiſe which is to abide within, in the Fathers Houſe for ever, for the ſeed of Bondage is not to be heir with the Free-born, neither to that ſeed do I write the words of my living and true Teſtimony, but to that which is juſt in every mans Conſcience, in the ſight of God do I deſire to be manifeſt, and ſo I ſhall be a ſweet ſavour, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in them that believe, but alſo in them that periſh, and if any have an ear to hear let him for his good.</p>
                  <p>And what if I ſay in truth on this wiſe, becauſe the Fear and Reverence of the Living Eternal Inviſible God is ſet up within my heart, therefore (and not otherwiſe) I cannot reſpect the perſons of any, neither give or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Honour and Glory of the world, Chriſt Jeſus my Lord being my Perfect and Compleat Example, alſo who ſaith, <hi>I receive not honour from man,</hi> and his very enemies who came to provoke, and tempt, and inſnare him, they diſcerned that he was a Juſt man, and that he reſpected not the perſon of any, as it is written of him, that ſaid to unbelievers on this wiſe, <hi>How can you believe which receive honour one of another, and ſeek not the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour which cometh from God onely, John</hi> 5. Mark that.</p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:54583:17"/>
                  <p>And I am right well and favourably perſwaded that as any of the Sons of men come to be honeſtly guided by a juſt, ſteadfaſt and equal Principle of God, as is the <hi>Light</hi> of Chriſt <hi>within them,</hi> to walk thereby in a juſt path, and equitable way, and in the ſame, at all times to ſpeak true, faſt, ſound, ſavoury and uncondemnable words and ſuch like actions to all with whom they have to do, and not to be hurtful or deſtructive to the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God, but alſo doing in the ſame light juſt and equitable things to all even as they would be done by, according to the perfect doctrine of Chriſt, the Law and the Prophets, I ſay the ſame will teſtifie for them, and make them truly honourable, and draw down Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, and not the contrary; and ſo in every Nation he that feareth God and worketh righteouſneſs is accepted of him, and theſe things will be acceptable and juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and not condemnable in the ſight and preſence of the everlaſting God, and ſo the true honour comes to be manifeſt which comes from God, whoſe eternal eye, the <hi>Light</hi> perfectly diſcerneth, and ſeeth into, and wiſely ſearcheth every mans heart <hi>within,</hi> and God is not devided from his eye, for as God is ſaid to be a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, ſo he is light, 1 <hi>Epiſt. John</hi> 1. from which no ſecret work of darkneſs can in any wiſe be hid, all be it the ſame be acted never ſo ſecretly. And behold I teſtifie in his Name that is true, that the ſound of his mighty day is come to the Nations, and the ſame terrible and glorious day hath begun to dawn in <hi>England</hi> in the <hi>North,</hi> and behold his everlaſting Light is ariſing over all Nations even the <hi>Light</hi> of the Lord Jeſus who light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the poor and deceitful mans eyes, yea he lightneth every man that cometh into the world with the Light that is perfect and true, either to condemn or juſtifie e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very mans words, thoughts and actions, and this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Light of eternity is manifeſtly ariſen up and hath its preheminence that is juſt in thouſands to the glory of the Lord who worketh both to will and to do in them that fear him, and have received of the fulneſs of his life
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:54583:18"/> in the ſame in which they live, and walk, and reſt, and ſo are become a bleſſing to the Nations in the Light of his eternal Countenance, in whom alſo they have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved unto Salvation, the tranſparent brightneſs of which through ſuch clouds of living witneſſes, is ſhining forth over the Nations, Kindreds, Tongues and Peoples that have corrupted the Earth, and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e degenerated and alienated in obſcurity under a thick vail of darkneſs in the night of Apoſtacy ſince the Holy Apoſtles days, from the Light and Life of the Inviſible and Immortal God and his Lamb the <hi>light</hi> who is coming in 10 thouſands of his Saints to convince all of their ungodlike words, Hard-ſpeeches, Thoughts and Actions, and to lead as many as receive and believe in the ſame Light with which they be enlightened from all ſin and unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſo from the condemnation of the ſame and wrath to come, even up to God the Father of all truth, from whence the Light, Life and every good thing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, according to the Propheſie of good old <hi>Enoch</hi> and the reſt of the Prophets, and bleſſed ſhall the Man, the Family, the City, the Kingdom, the Nation be that doth not wilfully and rebelliouſly reject, but receive and accept of the good day of their Viſitation of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of which I am one that giveth a certain ſound, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſaved by the ſame Grace and Life of God (that bringeth Salvation, and appeareth to all men, to the end that they may be ſaved by it alſo, and redeemed from Nations, Kindreds, Tongues and Peoples, for all the Earth was of one Language before <hi>Babel</hi> or <hi>Nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rods</hi> Generation of Builders was, and the Holy ſcriptures ſaith, <hi>That he was a mighty hunter before the Lord,</hi> who did and will confound their many Languages and Tongues that are out of the Truth and Plainneſſe, into which the ſons of men are to be redeemed from the contrary, for which my ſoul in love to the whole Creation travelleth, and my ſpirit in the ſame is ready to ſay Amen, to the counſel of the Everlaſting <hi>light</hi> in the truth, for the good and well-being of all the ſons of men, under what name
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:54583:18"/> or denomination ſoever they be called, albeit, I am as a ſtranger among them, and as an out-caſt or vile off-ſcouring of the world, and forſaken, but its not ſo with me of the Lord Almighty, whoſe ſervant and living witneſs I am, and his clean pure ſpirit of Life within my very Heart and Bowels beareth me record to the ſame in Peace, whether the ſons of men believe me or not, or hear or forbear, who ſcornfully call me a <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker,</hi> but in the <hi>Power of God</hi> do I work out my ſalvation <hi>with Fear and Trembling,</hi> according to the Holy Apoſtles ſound Doctrine and ſcriptures of Truth; And my name is known to the world (and to the ſaints in light upon the earth.)</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Genoa <date>
                           <hi>this firſt month, the tenth day, and of the year,</hi> 1662.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Daniel Baker.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>This was Rejected and not received by them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THe Holy Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> as the Scripture ſaith, (in his life) which giveth teſtimony unto this day on this wiſe, (to wit) that <hi>all Aſia had forſaken him,</hi> and what af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter there has been in theſe latter dayes among them cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Chriſtians, not only in <hi>Aſia,</hi> but alſo in all parts of the World where the joyful ſound hath come, but many rebell againſt the viſitation of life and ſalvation, ſo that they have rejected the word of the Lord, and its Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours of peace and ſaving health, which the moſt high hath ſent to and among them, and as the hard-hearted Jews in unbelief cryed <hi>help men of Iſrael,</hi> againſt two poor harmleſs Lambs in thoſe dayes of the Holy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, that were deemed by them to be ſuch <hi>as turned the World upſide down,</hi> and contrary to all men, on ſuch wiſe the ſame voice hath been ſounded <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orth and lifted up unwiſely by the ſame Spirit in <hi>Aſia</hi> againſt two plain na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Meſſengers and Miniſters of Truth; But how is it
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:54583:19"/> that wiſe men ſeem to be ſo vailed, or whats the matter that their underſtandings are ſo darkned from the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and the clear Spirit of diſcerning that of the Pure Immortal God, that they cannot ſee what they do, many of them whom my heart pitieth: Why ſhould ye be ſo affraid of the harmleſs and guiltleſs that ſounds the Meſſage of undeniable Truth, even the Word of the Lord which is the Sword of the Spirit, whoſe wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons are not carnal or viſible, as <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Judas</hi>'s were, but Spiritual, with the ſame to make war againſt Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual wickedneſſe, and to deſtroy and cut down that which rules even in high places, and in the Power of the Word Eternal to beat down and kill that which is hurtful and deſtructive to the Creation of God, in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Kingdoms, Thrones and Dominions, that the ſame Power of the gentle <hi>Lamb of God</hi> may rule in and over all as in the beginning, to the End that every man that liveth under the name or denomination of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, may clearly and truly ſay from his very heart [without mocking or provoking God Eternal to his Face] viz. AS IT WAS IN THE BEGIN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NING, SO IT IS NOW, AND EVER SHAL BE, And if the Sons of men did but ſuffer the fear of the Lord to poſſeſſe their hearts, and thereby honeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſider the weight of theſe words which ſo many vainly and unwiſely utter, they would in the firſt place fear and tremble, and not take the Name of the Lord ſo in vain, nor offer the ſacrifice of fools. But alas, theres few ſee as it was in the beginning, or how it is now, or what ſhall be in the World which hath no end, which is the ſame which in the beginning was, in which is the life which is the light of men, which men hate, becauſe their deeds are evil, which unfruitful works blinds the eye of a good and noble underſtanding, and therefore even a Mageſtrate, being ſo vailed, albeit in the place of Judicature, having a ſword in his hand, lifts it up and beareth it againſt the juſt and guiltleſſe, and ſo ſmites and wounds the Innocent, which ſhould be
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:54583:19"/> a terrour to the evil doer, and to them that do well not hurtful, but a praiſe; but otherwiſe it hath ſadly hapned in Ages and Generations even unto this our day againſt the <hi>Lamb,</hi> and his appearance in and through his Members, who hath been wounded and ſlain ſince the foundation of the World: And ſo it comes to paſſe through many that are in one and the ſame nature of tranſgreſſion, Even as a blind man, having a ſword in his hand, being haſty and as it were mad, layes it he knows not where, and ſmites he knows not what; And ſo he was a wiſe man that ſaid on this wiſe, to wit, <hi>Man being in honour and underſtandeth it not, is like the beaſt that periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now having a neceſſity in equitableneſſe to give forth theſe writings to publick view to a good end, for the good of all that hear and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern between the things that are of a good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port from what is otherwiſe condemnable and not juſtifiable in the ſight of God, neither of good men, and alſo ſeeing it is ſo, that plain Truth and its Friends, Followers and Meſſengers among the Nations (as its their portion to paſſe through the contradictions and manifold ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and reproaches of Chriſt their compleat ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample) are daily beſet with the ſame afflictions, and falſe reports from multitudes that are ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with open mouth, as in the dayes of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, <hi>Report ſay they, and we will report,</hi> yet we delight not to Retaliate any more then a good neceſſity from God Almighty lyeth on us, to give teſtimony for his Truth and Name and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ſake, for on this wiſe did the holy Prophets and Apoſtles as the holy Scriptures of Truth
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:54583:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> largely teſtifieth, as in the Books of <hi>Jeremy, Pſalms</hi> and the New Teſtament, and the <hi>Acts.</hi>
            </p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>This ſhall they have for their pride, becauſe they have reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and magnified themſelves, againſt the People of the Lord of hoſts, the Lord will be terrible unto them, for he will fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh all the gods of the earth, and men ſhall worſhip him, every one from his place, even all the Iſles of the Heathen, <bibl>
                     <hi>Zeph. 2.10, 11.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <closer>
               <signed>Daniel Baker.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
